[SPEAKER_00]: Bhante, as a spiritual practitioner, despite dedicating years to cultivating goodwill towards others, I still find occasional moments of ill-will surfacing.
[SPEAKER_00]: While I maintain faith in my chosen technique, I'm starting to feel fatigued by its repetitive nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe well, maybe happy, just imagining
[SPEAKER_00]: Goodwill and spreading it to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm curious if there's an alternative approach to sending goodwill to others that could rejuvenate my practice and infuse it with new energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no alternative way of sending anything to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to not act out of goodwill is to
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not through fabricating love towards others and pasting it over the basis of ill-will, the basis of irritation, the basis of greed, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only... the only way to truly have friendliness towards others in an unshakable manner, is if you have uprooted the basis for non-friendliness, for greed, for aversion, for distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're closer to practicing metta rightly, I must have said this before, if you're learning, if you're basically becoming able, if you're developing a skill of not acting out of your emotions, by body, by speech, and mentally as well, than by hundreds of years spent of spreading goodwill thoughts and love towards others.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just like applying a band-aid to an infected wound, without having the slightest notion of how to actually treat the infection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just hoping that the band-aid will extinguish the inflammation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will make it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's brewing underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the circumstances, you know, it can seem like it's working, like having thoughts and wishing people well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your circumstances are... you're probably living in an environment, you're not starting arguments, things are quite calm, so you're not getting angry, you're not in a circumstances which are inviting of arguments, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you not getting angry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is immovable?
[SPEAKER_01]: By the thoughts of irritation, or you're not getting angry because there's currently nothing annoying you, but if there were something, you would not be able to not get angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, it's not... it's not like... you can have good thoughts and think loving-kindness of people, if you want to make a practice out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just don't confuse it for the practice of metta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't confuse it for the practice of uprooting the ill-will, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just want to spend your day thinking nicely about people, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is when you think that those practices, those fabricated thoughts, would somehow magically uproot the liability to ill-will and irritations and resistance, that it's not about... it does not exist on the level of other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: The root of ill-will is the root of resistance towards your own physical presence and the feeling that's felt there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that patīgā that the suttas talk about, the resistance towards your own feeling, if it's unpleasant, that's the root of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is second to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole practice of friendliness is as basically as like the suttas describe very often.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like having purified your behavior way beforehand, established in virtue, established in right view, established in not acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you review the beginning, the core, here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any resistance here?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I will cultivate that framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-resistance towards anything that arises here on the level of feeling, within this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I shall direct that in every... direct that in every direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, I shall then look in every possible direction from here to see, is there any resistance towards anything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could there be any resistance towards anything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just basically expand the same framework that's already here unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if you're not resisting that unpleasant feeling... You can't be angry with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anger towards a person, towards something external, requires you to have already jumped on account of that resistance towards what's being felt here.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already averse towards the feeling that you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, so how do you tame the resistance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, how do you tame any craving in regard to any feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any of the three types of healing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, okay, so you want to tame your ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to tame your desires first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's another way of jumping on account of what's being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, in this sense, jumping towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jumping with craving, jumping with delight, with desire to have more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when something unpleasant touches you, you jump with the desire to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the whole, the whole practice of metta, it's like one of the, eh... it's the brahmavihāras.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the dwelling of the brahmas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the holy life, the celibate life, is called brahmacharya.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to dwell like a brahma, you can't just be having these... well, you can think that, but if you want to dwell like a brahma, means your whole life starts to... needs to begin to match that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you begin that by practice of celibacy, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you have no instruction about metta and positive thoughts towards others, by refraining from giving in to the physical desires, by refraining from basically desire of sensuality, you are faring around close to a brahma, like a brahma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to dwell like a brahma even more so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, on account of that purified livelihood,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not acting out of lust, not acting out of aversion, taming your mind, taming your senses through a sense restraint, enduring things rightly and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can look closer into, like, what's being felt here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are there traces of resistance towards that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by removing the resistance towards an unpleasant feeling here,
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be no external counterpart of ill-will towards the person out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you just protect that framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: Protect it in regard to any direction, anywhere in the world, upside down, from wherever it might come, the framework here of non-resistance remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not sending the framework to the East, North and West.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You protect it here from all these directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just a way of describing in the suttas that nowhere up, down, below, from any direction, nothing can come that can perturb the framework, because the mind has been tamed through establishment in virtue beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, having abandoned
[SPEAKER_01]: unskillful behavior, this is to say, he then dwells with the mind protected with friendliness, with the framework of friendliness, with the framework of compassion, and ultimately with the framework of equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The highest brahmavihāra is basically the equanimity, immovable, indifferent, completely, nothing felt, no movement there, whatsoever, doesn't matter what comes from what direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what brahmavihāras culminate
[SPEAKER_01]: With.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the highest one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could already see how your practice of sending positive thoughts is incompatible with the culmination of that practice of metta.
[SPEAKER_01]: If metta were to be sending of the positive thoughts, then surely, practice of indifference would be sending of indifferent thoughts, spreading indifference towards everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that work?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're actively engaging with it, you're not indifferent anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's about protecting of the framework, then the practice remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's the first brahmavihāra or the fourth, the principle remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I mean, like, instead of thinking, oh, I practice brahmavihāra by having wishful thinking and positive thoughts of other people, think that you practice brahmavihāra by being celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brahmacharya, brahmavihāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by being celibate, you are taming your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's... it's even without actively sort of trying to make it immovable, it's becoming more immovable.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to feelings, they will want to move it otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, sure, if you're already established in all of that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Skilled in that behavior, then you could now look even closer into, as I said, the traces of... would it move in regard to this or that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are the traces of... are the traces of aversion towards anything that could be felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards a change in the pleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there an aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there delight in... when the unpleasant feeling changes?
[SPEAKER_01]: And detach yourself from it and protect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Protect that state of mind.